Register of the Grand Duchess Ksenii͡a Aleksandrovna papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Grand Duchess Ksenii͡a Aleksandrovna papers
1865-1960
80011
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 cubic foot box, 1 envelope (7.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, diaries, printed matter, and photographs relating to events in Russia before, during, and after the Russian Revolution, and to Russian Imperial family matters. Includes letters of Nicholas II and his mother, Mariia Feodorovna.
Ksenii͡a Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess of Russia.
Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918.
Marīi͡a Ḟeodorovna, Empress, consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia, 1847-1928.
Access
Boxes 12-13 may not be used without permission of the Archivist; use copies are available in Boxes 6-8. Remainder of collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980, with an increment of additional materials acquired in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (13 reels).
Biographical Note
1875 March 25/April 7 Born to Mariia Feodorovna, Princess Dagmara of Denmark and Alexander III, Emperor of Russia
1894 April 1/14 Married Aleksandr Mikhailovich, Grand Duke of Russia (Sandro)
1895 July 3/16 Gave birth to Irina Aleksandrovna, Princess of Russia
1897 January 12/25 Gave birth to Andrei Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
1898 December 11/24 Gave birth to Fedor Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
1900 January 4/17 Gave birth to Nikita Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
1901 August 2/15 Gave birth to Dimitrii Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
1902 November 11/24 Gave birth to Rostislav Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
1907 June 24/July 7 Gave birth to Vasilii Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
1917 March 25 Traveled with her children to Ai-Todor, the estate in the Crimea that belonged to her husband Aleksandr Mikhailovich (the latter, Kseniia's mother Mariia Feodorovna, and her sister Olga with her husband had left for Ai-Todor on the 23rd). They were kept there under house arrest
1918 February Transferred, along with the family members mentioned above as well as her son-in-law Felix Yusupov and her granddaughter, to Dulber, the fortress-like estate also in the Crimea belonging to Grand Duke Petr Nikolaevich. (The latter and his brother, Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich, their wives, and Peter's children, had gone to Duil'ber after the fall of the monarchy.)
1919 April Sailed from Yalta (along with several members of her family, her mother Mariia Feodorovna, and other relatives) on the HMS Marlborough, sent by her cousin George V, King of England (the Allied fleet had arrived in the Crimea at the end of 1918)
1919 May Arrived in England
1919-1928 Made frequent visits to her mother in Denmark, until the death of Mariia Feodorovna in 1928
1919-1936 Lived in Frogmore Cottage, Windsor Palace
1936-1960 Lived in Wilderness House, Hampton Court, again as a guest of the British royal family
1960 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Kseniia Aleksandrovna were deposited in the Hoover Institution by her family in 1980, under the supervision of her son the late Vasili Romanoff, who served as honorary curator of the Hoover Institution Archives Imperial Russian Collection.
Of particular interest are her diaries, covering the period from January 1916 to March 1919, the day before she left the Crimea for England. Also significant is the correspondence between her and her brother, Emperor Nicholas II, and between him and their mother, Empress Mariia Feodorovna. Those original diaries and letters, in Boxes 12-13, may not be used without permission of the Archivist, but use copies are available in Boxes 6-8.
Other diaries of note are those of Mariia Feodorovna (in Box 9) and of Kseniia's brother, Grand Duke Mikhail Aleksandrovich (in Box 11), as well as a diary presumed to have been kept for the crown prince Aleksei by his French and English tutors (in Box 8).
The bulk of the collection relates to Mariia Feodorovna, consisting of extensive correspondence with her daughter Kseniia (Boxes 1-6) and with others (Boxes 8-9), and of condolence letters upon her death in 1928 (Boxes 9-10).
The increment consists mainly of correspondence with family members in the United States and Europe, and various royal figures from the United Kingdom, Denmark, Sweden, Germany, Greece, Bulgaria, Romania, and Yugoslavia. Correspondence includes handwritten (mostly unidentified) letters on political, social, religious, educational, and economic conditions in Russia. The increment also contains a number of remarkable prints depicting members of the royal family.
Romanov, House of.; Russia--Court and courtiers.; Russia--History--Nicholas II, 1894-1917.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
- Correspondence, 1904-1929 (Boxes 1-6)
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Aleksandr Mikhailovich, Grand Duke of Russia
    - (1), 1919 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - (3), 1921 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - (37), 1922 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - (13), 1928 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - (25), 1929 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Alexandra Feodorovna, Empress, consort of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia (1), 1917 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Anastasiia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess of Russia (1), 1918 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Andrei Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (8), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    General note
    See also El'sa, Princess of Russia
  - Dimitrii Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (6), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - El'za, Princess of Russia (6), 1921-1929 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Fedor Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (18), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Irina Aleksandrovna, Princess of Russia (14), 1904-1929 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Iusupov, Feliks, Prince (1), 1922 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Iusupova, Irina [See: Irina Aleksandrovna, Princess of Russia]
  - Mariia, Princess of Russia (13), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    See also Nikita Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia
  - Mariia Feodorovna, Empress, consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia
    - (17), 1914 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - (32), 1915 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - 1916
      - (30), January-August (Box-folder 1: 17)
      - (38), September-December (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - (52), 1917 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - (47), 1918 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - (44), 1919 (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
    - 1920
      - (36), January-March (Box-folder 2: 6)
      - (54), April-December (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
    - (33), 1921 (Box-folder 3: 3-4)
    - 1922
      - (49), January-September (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
      - (25), October-December (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - (61), 1923 (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
    - (59), 1924 (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
    - (115), 1925 (Box-folder 5: 1-4)
    - (73), 1926 (Box-folder 5: 5-6)
    - (67), 1927 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
    - (18), 1928 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Mariia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess of Russia (2), 1917-1918 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia (6), 1917-1918 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Use copies (originals in Box 13)
  - Nikita Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (34), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Ol'ga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess of Russia (1), 1916 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess of Russia (4), 1917-1918 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Rostislav Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (6), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Tat'iana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess of Russia (2), 1917-1918 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Vasilii Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (15), 1922-1929 (Box-folder 6: 11)
- Diaries, 1916-1919 (Boxes 6-7)
  Use copies (originals in Box 12), arranged chronologically.
  - 1916 January-September (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - 1916 September - 1917 March (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - 1917 March-August (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - 1917 August - 1918 January (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - 1918 January-June (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - 1918 June-November (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - 1918 November - 1919 March (Box-folder 7: 5)
- Subject File, 1866-1929 (Boxes 8-11)
  Correspondence, diaries, menus, poems, reports, visitors' book, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject. Consists mostly of material relating to Mariia Feodorovna, consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia.
  - Aleksandra Iosifovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1869 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Report on the Grand Duchess' journey from Nice, France, to Geneva, Switzerland.
  - Aleksei Nikolaevich, Czarevitch, son of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1917 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    Diary presumably kept by his tutors, relating to his daily activities for January and February 1917, written both in French and English. Also lists birth and baptism dates of Romanov family members.
  - Churchill, Reginald, "Easter Day, " sermon, holograph, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Creative writing - collection of poems by unidentified author(s), handwritten copies (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Finland (Box-folder 8: 5)
    Clippings, letter, printed matter
  - Grandchildren of Kseniia Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, and Aleksandr Mikhailovich, Grand Duke, correspondence (19), 1929 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Mariia Feodorovna, Empress, consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia
    - General
      - Correspondence
        - General (12), 1916-1918 (Box-folder 8: 7)
        - Unidentified correspondents (15), 1891-1918 (Box-folder 8: 8)
          Consists of letters either by Mariia Feodorovna or addressed to her
        - Aleksandr Mikhailovich, Grand Duke of Russia (1), 1927 (Box-folder 8: 9)
        - Aleksei Nikolaevich, Czarevitch, son of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia (2), 1916-1917 (Box-folder 8: 10)
        - Alexandra, Queen, consort of Edward VII, King of Great Britain (17), 1918-1926 (Box-folder 8: 11)
        - Alexandra Feodorovna, Empress, consort of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 12)
        - Anastasiia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess (1), 1916 (Box-folder 8: 13)
        - Bariatinskaia, Nadine, Princess (2), 1919 (Box-folder 8: 14)
        - Benkendorf, Pavel, Count (2), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 15)
        - Calthorpe, Arthur, Sir, Vice-Admiral (3), 1918-1919 (Box-folder 8: 16)
        - Christian X, King of Denmark (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 17)
        - Churchill, Reginald (1), undated (Box-folder 8: 18)
        - Davidson, Arthur, Sir, Colonel (1), 1920 (Box-folder 8: 19)
        - Davydov (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 20)
        - Dimitrii Aleksandrovich, Prince of Russia (8), 1915-1926 (Box-folder 8: 21)
        - Fon Tal', Iakov (2), 1921 (Box-folder 8: 22)
        - George, Duke of Kent? (1), undated (Box-folder 8: 23)
        - George V, King of Great Britain (2 plus transcription of 1 telegram), 1919 (Box-folder 8: 24)
        - Georgii Mikhailovich, Grand Duke of Russia (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 25)
        - Gervais, Vice-Admiral (1), 1919 (Box-folder 8: 26)
        - Gorchakova, Mariia (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 27)
        - Hird? Ol'ga (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 28)
        - Kleinmikhel, Ekaterina (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 29)
        - Kukushkina, L. (1), undated (Box-folder 8: 30)
        - League for Restoration of Russian Monarchy (1), 1918 (Box-folder 8: 31)
        - Louise, Queen, consort of Frederick VIII, King of Denmark (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 32)
        - Marie, Queen, consort of Ferdinand I, King of Romania (Missy) (2), 1918 (Box-folder 8: 33)
        - Mariia Aleksandrovna, Empress, consort of Alexander II, Emperor of Russia (1), 1866 (Box-folder 8: 34)
        - Mariia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess (3), 1916-1917 (Box-folder 8: 35)
        - Meiendorf, Vera (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 36)
        - Mikhail Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke (10), 1916-1917 (Box-folder 8: 37)
        - Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia (8), 1916-1918 (Box-folder 8: 38)
        - Nikolai Mikhailovich, Grand Duke (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 39)
        - Ol'ga Konstantinovna, Queen, consort of George I, King of Greece (10), 1917-1922 (Box-folder 8: 40)
        - Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess (8), 1916-1918 (Box-folder 8: 41)
        - Orblliani, Vera (1), undated (Box-folder 8: 42)
        - Ozerova, Ekaterina (2), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 43)
        - Paskevich, J. (1), 1917 (Box-folder 8: 44)
        - Prince, John Dyneley (1), 1927 (Box-folder 8: 45)
        - Roche, C. (1), 1919 (Box-folder 8: 46)
        - Tatishcheva, Ekaterina (1), 1917 (Box-folder 9: 1)
        - Tat'iana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess (3), 1916 (Box-folder 9: 2)
        - Tolstaia (Sazonova), Mariia (1), 1917 (Box-folder 9: 3)
        - Tolstoi, Sergei (1), 1917 (Box-folder 9: 4)
        - Trubetskaia, Aleksandra (1), 1919 (Box-folder 9: 5)
        - Veselovskii? (1), 1916 (Box-folder 9: 6)
        - Vrangel', Petr (1), 1921 (Box-folder 9: 7)
        - Waldemar, Prince of Denmark (3), 1917 (Box-folder 9: 8)
      - Diaries, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 9: 9)
      - Menus (Box-folder 9: 10)
      - Visitors' book (Box-folder 9: 11)
    - Death of Mariia Feodorovna, 1928 October 13
      Letters of condolence (each folder contains one letter unless otherwise noted).
      - Unidentified (27) (Box-folder 9: 12)
      - Al'brikhovich, Petr (Box-folder 9: 13)
      - Anastasii, Archbishop (Box-folder 9: 14)
      - Antonii, Metropolitan (2) (Box-folder 9: 15)
      - Bagration-Mukhranskaia, Nina, Princess (Box-folder 9: 16)
      - Baliasnaia, Liudmila (Box-folder 9: 17)
      - Bariatinskaia, Mariia (Box-folder 9: 18)
      - Bel'gard, B. (Box-folder 9: 19)
      - Bezak, Elena (Box-folder 9: 20)
      - Bezobrazov, Guards Captain of Cavalry (Box-folder 9: 21)
      - Bezobrazova, Nadezhda (Box-folder 9: 22)
      - Blakeslee, Victor (Box-folder 9: 23)
      - Bobrinskaia, Ol'ga (Box-folder 9: 24)
      - Brant, Evgenii, Captain of Cavalry (Box-folder 9: 25)
      - Crofts, Melicent (Box-folder 9: 26)
      - Davydova, Dar'ia (Box-folder 9: 27)
      - De Chateauneuf, Allan (Box-folder 9: 28)
      - De Chateauneuf, Henriette A. (Box-folder 9: 29)
      - De la Roche Guyon, Marquis (Box-folder 9: 30)
      - Demchenko, Evgenii (Box-folder 9: 31)
      - Demidova, Sof'ia (Box-folder 9: 32)
      - De Stoecke, Alfred (Box-folder 9: 33)
      - Dimitrii Pavlovich, Grand Duke of Russia? (Box-folder 9: 34)
      - Dolgorukova, Aleksandra (Box-folder 9: 35)
      - Domozhirov, Sergei (Box-folder 9: 36)
      - Eagen, Margarete (Box-folder 9: 37)
      - Ebelin, Mariia (Box-folder 9: 38)
      - Eimer, Mariia (Box-folder 9: 39)
      - Engel'gardt, Sof'ia, Baroness (Box-folder 9: 40)
      - Evreinov, S. (Box-folder 9: 41)
      - Evreinova, Anna (Box-folder 9: 42)
      - Fenton, Margery (Box-folder 9: 43)
      - Fersen, Asia (Box-folder 9: 44)
      - Gagarina, Tat'iana (Box-folder 9: 45)
      - Gardner, Frank (Box-folder 9: 46)
      - Gardner, Marie (Box-folder 9: 47)
      - Gartman, Mary (Box-folder 9: 48)
      - George, Duke of Kent? (Box-folder 9: 49)
      - George V, King of Great Britain (Box-folder 9: 50)
      - Georgievskii, Aleksandr (Box-folder 9: 51)
      - Ginand (Vyvodtseva), Mariia (Box-folder 9: 52)
      - Golitsyna, Aleksandra (Box-folder 9: 53)
      - Golitsyna, Ekaterina (Box-folder 9: 54)
      - Golitsyna, Merika (Box-folder 9: 55)
      - Gordienko, K. (Box-folder 9: 56)
      - Grabbe (Obolenskaia), Mariia (Box-folder 9: 57)
      - Grabbe, Mikhail, Count (Box-folder 9: 58)
      - Gregori, Emma (Box-folder 9: 59)
      - Grickham, A. Z., Captain of Royal Navy (Box-folder 9: 60)
      - Grigor'ev, Aleksandr (Box-folder 9: 61)
      - Gruzinskaia, A., Princess (Box-folder 9: 62)
      - Goujon, M. (Box-folder 9: 63)
      - Haakon VII, King of Norway (Charles) (Box-folder 9: 64)
      - Humphrey, Alice (Box-folder 9: 65)
      - Iakushev, V. (Box-folder 9: 66)
      - Ierones? A., Colonel (Box-folder 9: 67)
      - Ignat'eva (Urusova), Mariia (Box-folder 9: 68)
      - Il'ina (Kornilova), E. (Box-folder 9: 69)
      - Izvol'skaia, Mimi (Box-folder 9: 70)
      - Johnson, D., Vice-Admiral (Box-folder 9: 71)
      - Kantakuzina, May (Box-folder 9: 72)
      - Kantakuzina, Ol'ga (Box-folder 9: 73)
      - Kantakuzina-Speranskaia, Iuliia (Box-folder 9: 74)
      - Kaul'berg, Aleksandr (Box-folder 9: 75)
      - Kazbek (Dadiani, Princess), Nina (Box-folder 9: 76)
      - Kedrov, Nikolai (Box-folder 9: 77)
      - Kirova, Dar'ia, Countess (Box-folder 9: 78)
      - Kleinmikhel', Mariia, Countess (Box-folder 9: 79)
      - Kleinmikhel', Vladimir (Box-folder 9: 80)
      - Kochubei, Elena (Box-folder 9: 81)
      - Kokovtsev, V., Count (Box-folder 9: 82)
      - Kologrivova (Dumbadze), Nina (Box-folder 9: 83)
      - Komov, P. (Box-folder 9: 84)
      - Komova, M. (Box-folder 9: 85)
      - Korybut-Dashkevich, Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - Kovalev, Petr (Box-folder 10: 2)
      - Kozakovskii, Nikolai (Box-folder 10: 3)
      - Kum, A. (Box-folder 10: 4)
      - Kuralin, Ivan (Box-folder 10: 5)
      - Kuryndin, Georgii (Box-folder 10: 6)
      - Kutuzova, Vera (Box-folder 10: 7)
      - Lazareva, E. (Box-folder 10: 8)
      - Levitskii (Box-folder 10: 9)
      - Levshin, Boris, Captain of Cavalry (Box-folder 10: 10)
      - Levshin, M., Major-General (Box-folder 10: 11)
      - Liven, Anatolii, Prince (Box-folder 10: 12)
      - Louise, Princess Royal (Box-folder 10: 13)
      - Makarova, Ekaterina (Box-folder 10: 14)
      - Makarova (Segiurlerg), Mariia (Box-folder 10: 15)
      - Maksimovich, Pavel (Box-folder 10: 16)
      - Mamontova, Ekaterina (Box-folder 10: 17)
      - Mary, Queen, consort of George V, King of Great Britain (May) (Box-folder 10: 18)
      - Maslennikova, Sekira (Box-folder 10: 19)
      - Matveev, Aleksei (Box-folder 10: 20)
      - Maud, Princess (Maudie) (Box-folder 10: 21)
      - Maud, Queen, consort of Haakon VII, King of Norway (Box-folder 10: 22)
      - May, Lady (Box-folder 10: 23)
      - Meiendorf (Golenishcheva-Kutuzova), Sof'ia (Box-folder 10: 24)
      - Meshcherskaia, M., Princess (Box-folder 10: 25)
      - Meshcherskaia, Vera, Princess (Box-folder 10: 26)
      - Militsa Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess of Russia (Box-folder 10: 27)
      - Miloradovich, Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 28)
      - Mochalov, Ippolit (Box-folder 10: 29)
      - Murav'ev-Apostol (Box-folder 10: 30)
      - Naryshkin, Vadim (Box-folder 10: 31)
      - Nazymova, Sabina (Box-folder 10: 32)
      - Nevrazhina, Liudmila (Box-folder 10: 33)
      - Niquille, Al (Box-folder 10: 34)
      - Nikitina, L. (Box-folder 10: 35)
      - Nikolai, Grand Duke of Greece? (Box-folder 10: 36)
      - Nikolai, Head Priest of Russian Orthodox Church in London (Box-folder 10: 37)
      - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke of Russia (Box-folder 10: 38)
      - Nilova, Marianna (Box-folder 10: 39)
      - Nitsenko, Dar'ia (Box-folder 10: 40)
      - Obolenskaia, E. (Box-folder 10: 41)
      - Obolenskaia, Natal'ia (Box-folder 10: 42)
      - Officers of Household Cavalry of Empress Mariia Feodorovna (Box-folder 10: 43)
      - Ogilby, R. B. (Box-folder 10: 44)
      - Ol'denburgskaia, Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 45)
      - Ol'shevskii, Georgii (Box-folder 10: 46)
      - Ostich-Rabich, R. (Box-folder 10: 47)
      - Pachich, Georgine N. (Box-folder 10: 48)
      - Panteleeva, M. (Box-folder 10: 49)
      - Paparigopulo, Aleksandr (Box-folder 10: 50)
      - Pashkevich-Balasheva, E. (Box-folder 10: 51)
      - Peel, Arthur (Box-folder 10: 52)
      - Plonskaia, Vera (Box-folder 10: 53)
      - Poltoratskaia, Elena (Box-folder 10: 54)
      - Popov, Nikolai, Head Priest of Russian Orthodox Church in Pau, France (Box-folder 10: 55)
      - Prince, Adeline (Box-folder 10: 56)
      - Putiatin, Sergei, Prince? (Box-folder 10: 57)
      - Putiatina (Mariia Pavlovna, Grand Duchess of Russia), Mariia (Box-folder 10: 58)
      - Radziwill, Marie Rose, nee Countess Branicki (Bichette) (Box-folder 10: 59)
      - Richards, Julia (Box-folder 10: 60)
      - Sablin, E. (Box-folder 10: 61)
      - Sablina, Nadezhda (Box-folder 10: 62)
      - Sazonova, Rina (Box-folder 10: 63)
      - Semenova-Tian'shanskaia, Nina (Box-folder 10: 64)
      - Serafim, Bishop (Box-folder 10: 65)
      - Seymons, Blanchie (Box-folder 10: 66)
      - Seymons, Edward (Box-folder 10: 67)
      - Shakhovskaia, Mariia (Box-folder 10: 68)
      - Shatalin, Vladimir (Box-folder 10: 69)
      - Shebeko, A. (Box-folder 10: 70)
      - Shebeko, Vadim (Box-folder 10: 71)
      - Sheina, E. (Box-folder 10: 72)
      - Sheremet'ev, Sergei (Box-folder 10: 73)
      - Sheremet'eva, Anastasiia (Box-folder 10: 74)
      - Sheremet'eva, Mariia (Box-folder 10: 75)
      - Shtakel'berg (Kaul'berg), Mariia, Baroness (Box-folder 10: 76)
      - Shuvalova, Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 77)
      - Sipiagin, N. (Box-folder 10: 78)
      - Stepankovskii, Boris (Box-folder 10: 79)
      - Stewart, Herbert E. (Box-folder 10: 80)
      - Stresova, Teresa (Box-folder 10: 81)
      - Strukova, Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 82)
      - Strutfield, Henry (Box-folder 10: 83)
      - Tolstaia (Shuvalova), Mariia (Box-folder 10: 84)
      - Tolstaia, Zinaida (Box-folder 10: 85)
      - Tolstoi, D. I., Count (Box-folder 10: 86)
      - Tomson-Konshina, Sof'ia (Box-folder 10: 87)
      - Trubetskaia, Mariia (Box-folder 10: 88)
      - Trubetskaia, Meri (Box-folder 10: 89)
      - Uvarov, Sergei (Box-folder 10: 90)
      - Vasil'chikova, Sof'ia (Box-folder 10: 91)
      - Veimarus, Natal'ia (Box-folder 10: 92)
      - Vonliarskaia, Sofia (Box-folder 10: 93)
      - Vera Konstantinovna, Princess of Russia (Box-folder 10: 94)
      - Verkhovskoi, P. (Box-folder 10: 95)
      - Viazemskaia, M., Princess (Box-folder 10: 96)
      - Victoria, Princess Royal (Box-folder 10: 97)
      - Volkonskaia (Luchinina), Mariia (Box-folder 10: 98)
      - Voronov, Pavel (Box-folder 10: 99)
      - Vorontsov, Roman (Box-folder 10: 100)
      - Vrangel', Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 101)
      - Vvedenskaia, Agnesa (Box-folder 10: 102)
      - Zbyshevskaia, Mariia (Box-folder 10: 103)
      - Zherebtsov, Dmitrii (Box-folder 10: 104)
      - Zhirar, Ol'ga (Box-folder 10: 105)
      - Zinov'ev, Aleksandr (Box-folder 10: 106)
      - Zinov'ev, Dmitrii (Box-folder 10: 107)
      - Zvegintseva, Sof'ia (Box-folder 10: 108)
      - Zykova (Box-folder 10: 109)
    - Prayer for Russia (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Press on (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Refugees, Russian (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - World War, 1914-1918 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Mikhail Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke of Russia, diaries, 1911-1914 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke of Russia - resignation from the position of Commander-in-Chief of the Russian army, correspondence, 1917 March (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Novikoff, Ol'ga, "Russia and Europe," Asiatic Review, printed copy, 1922 October (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Rasputin, Grigorii, 1919 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    Report of Deputy Attorney of Ekaterinodar region Vladimir Rudnev on relationship between Grigorii Rasputin and members of the Imperial family.
  - Songs, Russian (Box-folder 11: 9)
- Original Diaries and Correspondence, 1916-1919 (Boxes 12-13)
  Access
  Boxes 12-13 may not be used without permission of the Archivist.
  Original diaries of Kseniia Aleksandrovna, 1916 January - 1919 March (use copies in Boxes 6-7); original correspondence between her and Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1917-1918 (use copies in Box 6); original letters from Nicholas II to Mariia Feodorovna, 1916-1918 (use copies in Box 8).
  - Original diaries of Kseniia Aleksandrovna
    Box 12 may not be used without permission of the Archivist (use copies in Boxes 6-7).
    - 1916 January 1 - September 15 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - 1916 September 16 - 1917 March 27 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - 1917 March 28 - August 23 (Box-folder 12: 3)